{
  "reference_number": "4999",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The proposed Climate Change Commission may recommend that the NZ parliament change the 2050 target if and only if there are\n\n major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements concerning climate change. The legislation should require a\n 75% majority in any parliamentary vote to effect the recommended change."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The proposed Climate Change Commission may recommend that the third emissions budget be changed if and only if there are\n major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements concerning climate change. The legislation should require a\n\n 75% majority in any parliamentary vote to effect the recommended change."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Not under any circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The legislation should require the Government to set out it's plans to achieve emissions budgets within six months from the date\n\nthey are issued by the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Local Government should be legally obliged to consider the Climate Change Commission's recommendations in their planning.\nStrong coordination with business groups. Ensure that individuals who lose jobs or income as a result of these plans are offered\n\nmeaningful opportunities for alternative employment. LEAD BY EXAMPLE. Ambitious, forward looking goals - eg eliminate the sale or\nimport of fossil fuel powered cars by 2030."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should provide a progress report in the last quarter of every Parliamentary term before elections are\nheld."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Climate change will affect every New Zealander irrespective of race, creed or gender so it is not appropriate that Maori interests\nshould have a special, privileged voice on the Commission or be given special consideration. There should also be members who\n\nhave expertise in energy systems and ecosystems as these have been omitted from the list on page 45 of the discussion document."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be a separate adaptation sub-committee within the Climate Commission based on the UK model."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Stop people building in areas that will be drowned by sea level rise."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Scientists started warning us about the dangers of climate change over thirty years ago and yet we have done almost nothing to\naddress the problem in this country. We need to stop talking about it and start incentivizing radical change. Please get on with it.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
